all right hello and welcome it's June
4th
6424 and we are in active inference live
stream
57.2 welcome to the active inference
Institute we're a participatory online
Institute that is communicating learning
and practicing applied active inference
you can find us at the link on this page
this is recorded and archived live
stream so please provide feedback so we
can improve our work all backgrounds and
perspectives are welcome and we'll
follow video etiquette for live
streams head over to active inference
dorg to learn more about projects and
today in
57.2 we'll jump right into it with a new
guest Frasier and picking up on some
topics that we left from the do one plus
any other things that come up so by way
of getting started Frasier you want to
say hello and then any recap slash
anything that you're thinking about
would be exciting to discuss
today hello yes so my name is Fraser I
hope everyone can hear me okay uh so I'm
I'm a recent computer science uh honest
graduate from the University of Western
Australia my interest is very much ly in
in applying active inference in sort of
Inu real world you know real time
processing and so forth so I'm I'm very
much interested by the the way in which
organisms can well artificial or
otherwise can use active inference to
sort of build an an Eco Niche that
affords their their adaptivity over time
of course that's quite a general
statement but doing this in real time is
is quite difficult and if we can get a
way
to optimize on how we're soliciting data
you know soliciting data intelligently
and so forth where going to be able to
do that much more effectively than we
have in the past so that's a little bit
about where my interests lie uh and I'm
particularly interested in the consan is
between this paper and this Suite of
ideas uh with another emerging framework
in in cognitive science called relevance
realization I think there's there's
quite a bit to be had there so that's a
little bit about me and my interests so
thank
you
cool Thomas what would you say just
right off the bat in terms of relevance
realization and active data s
or or what else would you want to sample
to know how you could
answer I'd want to know more about um
about relevance realization and and what
that involves it's not something I have
any expertise
in well excellent I think we'll be able
to um to have a bit of a back and forth
then so sounds great yeah go for it fer
how would you bring it in and then we'll
see where it goes well it is I must
stress it is a a an emerging framework
there are several papers on precisely
named as such you know relevance
realization an emerging framework in in
uh cognitive science but the general
idea and this is very much spearheaded
by I would say John V of the University
of Toronto and a few other people Mark
Miller in in um the University of monach
here in
Australia the the idea the central idea
is that the ability to zero in on
relevant information is is the Criterion
of the cognitive so you know there are
cognitive agents we are all cognitive
agents um trying to make cognitive
agents in active inference what exactly
does that entail the the hypothesis is
that to the extent that you are a
cognitive agent you're able to to zero
in on the relevant information that is
uh necessary for maintaining your
survival across time and your your
ability to to achieve certain goals
certain goals that one would expect are
constitutive of your autop poesis as as
an organism um and so the question then
becomes okay well what what what
precisely does this mean how can we cash
out what it means to to look for
relevance in an
environment you know classically this is
going to involve avoiding things that
deleterious to our our markof blanket
and and seeking out things that are
conducive to it um the only other thing
I would say so that that's that's a bit
of a broad discussion the only other
thing I would say is that it's it's very
much stressed in I would say the work of
AI and and colleagues that we actually
cannot end up with a theory of relevance
per se nothing is canonically relevant
so things things might be relevant in so
far as they are large or in so far as
they are small or in so far as they live
for a short amount of time or they have
you know they R selected or k selected
there is nothing that is uh you know
relevant in in any absolute sense but
what we might be able to do is have a
theory of relevance realization that is
to say the processes and mechanisms and
trade-off relationships that allow and
afford for the realization of relevance
uh well one more thing the the the
emphasis is on
that that web realization is quite
important uh the the framework does not
presuppose that relevance is sort of out
there in the world and we merely detect
relevance neither is it assumed that we
simply uh Express uh something from
within our own schema in a sort of you
know romantic idea where just sort of
Express relevance relevance is
co-created in the you know sense of
motor Loop the econ between the agent
internet's environment so so I mean all
of these ideas are very very broadly
consilient with uh the active inference
you know framework more generally uh so
I thought this would be a Kind of
Perfect Place to um to bring this this
other framework in I know I'm sorry
Thomas that I'm sort of blindsiding you
here with respect to this this Theory
but um I think the general discussion
that we will have even if we don't focus
on you know the particular theory of say
relevance realization per se will very
much swim in the same sort of waters
that I'm interested in in in navigating
so I hope that makes some sort of sense
absolutely and thank you for explaining
it um the thought that came to my mind
is if you sort of go back a little bit
in and psychology what what's the
relationship between the idea of
relevance there and the idea of
savs would you say the two are in some
way analogous or is one subser of the
other well one so the the framework in
so far as I'm familiar with with it the
idea is that relevance is in relevance
really Iz ation is perhaps isomorphic or
at least deeply uh very much
deeply you know bed fellows with
predictive processing so the idea would
be that the the mechanism of say
Precision waiting is is very very uh
very much shared by by all of the
processes that underwrite relevance
realization so to the extent that
predictive processing and precision
waiting uh have things to say about
salience as opposed to relevance more
generally construed I suppose uh there
would not be much of a distinction to be
to be made but so to try and answer your
question the the the uh you know
consilience are very much
between the idea about self dynamical
self-organization over sets of trade-off
relationships that's essentially what
relevance
realization uh you know the ontology of
relevance realization the the
isomorphism is between that and
precision waiting in predictive
processing that's the very specific
mechanism that is that is
identified okay so that that's an
interesting point to sort of consider
and one of the reasons I think that's
quite interesting is is to
think is there anything intrinsic about
relevance that requires action um do are
my actions in a in a clear way
determined by it because one one could
imagine having an attentional system
that just Precision weights based upon
some passive data to work out which
stream is going to be most
informative in updating beliefs without
actually acting in any way to change it
whereas the concept of sence I think
goes a little bit beyond that and says
actually it's not just a matter that I'm
I'm estimating how precise the data
streams that I'm getting are I'm
actually choosing those data
streams right where approximately do you
think it would
sit uh okay in that in that sort of
schema I would I would very much say
it's within the salience kind of
landscape uh the the emphasis is very
much on the the the means by which we
can adaptively interact with our
environment to solicit the right
observations that are you know condusive
to our agency per do you mind then just
I suppose ripping on the the exact kind
of definition of of salience as you've
already done it I suppose but that that
might be
helpful discussion as well I I think
it's an interesting one and and probably
if you asked five or six different
people you get five or six different
definitions would um and I think you
know I don't want to put my definition
as being in any way Superior to to
anybody else's but the the way I tend to
think about
it is that attention as you say is
effectively a process of game control
it's working out how precise of the
different modalities that are available
to me and that can be various different
levels it can be a sort of spatial
channels that I want to emphasize in
spatial attention it might be attending
to particular features
um and there are various different
versions of it um the distinction I'd
make with salience is that I think
salience is something that will actually
drive action it's the amount normally I
think of it in terms of the amount of
Information Gain I would associate with
several different actions and so the the
degree to which I'm drawn towards
doing that also raises the question then
of what do I mean by doing something um
because I could be doing something by
overtly moving my eyes towards it
but we may be able to loop back around
and say well actually there's also the
possibility to do something without
making any explicit action but by
choosing to allocate more of my or
choosing a model in which I allocate
more Precision to a particular Channel
compared to another um but I think it it
relies Upon A weighing up of
Alternatives that there are several
different things I could do here uh and
a selection between
those of course how I select between
different actions will also depend upon
the Precision that I ascribed
different or the modalities that I might
be able to observe following those
actions because if something is more
precise then that also implies less
ambiguous and has the potential to to
allow me to gain more
information so you you see immediately
why all these Concepts end up quite
conflated because they do you know quite
sensibly some ways um they do all feed
into one another in quite a profound way
um but I think it's sometimes useful
just to be able to separate out the
process of describing Precision to
something from the process of choosing
between several Alternatives in order
that I can gain the most
information right yes because
specifically with that information gain
there is of course the perhaps
equivocation between say which model are
we going to deploy to to you know make
sense of the the sensory erors and so
forth and then so exactly what
observations are we going to pay
attention to so that that issue is
perhaps you know one that needs to be
finessed um and I would say more more
particularly relevance realization is is
uh at least historically uh comes from
the issue of model selection so the the
the emphasis was very much on how the
framework might be able to address the
frame problem in Psychology so which you
have a particular schema that you're
bringing to bear on the way in which
you're dynamically self organizing
around your sensory prediction errors
that's within a particular model um the
yeah so historically that's been the
focus I would say which would fit more
precisely with with model selection as
opposed to just uh the the key sort of
you know base raw salience of of any
particular observation so there almost a
form of covert sence attribution isn't
it not necessarily acting in the sense
of moving but acting in a a covert
mental action to select between some
Alternatives have
that yes yes there is a there was an
action in terms of which model is
deployed and in that respect it is very
much you know action of the praic kind
of the deflationary kind as KL might say
of you you know moving your your finger
or carding your ey and so forth that is
that is definitely part of very much
included in the relevance realization
framework but um yeah that it does go
all the way up to and is largely
concerned with the question of model
selection
as we might pose in a machine learning
context this I think that's incred sorry
D do you want to go ahead go go I I was
just going to say I think that that's a
really nice perspective really important
perspective to bring in in this
particular discussion sort of around
themes that we've been discussing over
the last couple of live streams as well
um about um the importance of selecting
your
data and that only comes about when
you're capable of a particular kind of
action
and it's worth thinking about why
particular kinds of action like this are
so important and one of the reasons may
just be a matter of efficiency that if
you can select relatively small portions
of the data that are going to be
relevant then you don't have to process
everything at once um arguably that's
the reason we don't have you know many
many eyes pointing in all different
directions because we don't need to we
just need something with a very high
focus at a FAL level uh that we can use
to specifically select the information
we want to at any one point in
time on this salience question it
reminds me of the classic two two
options to dissipate the free energy
with change the mind to change the world
so in terms of changing the world or at
least what it hands to you there's the
over choice of which stream of data to
sample from that's like moving the eyes
and then on the change the mind there's
the inner salience landscape inner
relevance
realization that given a fixed stream of
observations still enables a degree of
freedom in selecting models that provide
epistemic
value what what is the pragmatic
counterpart to
salience expected utility associated
with an action
yeah I think that's
probably again it comes down to lots of
different words possibly with different
meanings but also lots of different
meanings that sorry lots of the same
meanings that have lots of different
words and so you're probably right to
say pragmatic value expected utility um
expected reward in some communities um
the negative cost um there are all sorts
of words you could use that more or less
mean the same thing and what that means
is is um just a description of something
being attractive or aversive and even
that is itself a little bit torical
because it's just saying um my
description for why a particular
Behavior has occurred is that there is
something that this particular Behavior
or or or that will will bias behavior
towards or away from
it so it's almost quite a simple idea
which is that that the behavior depends
upon attractive or aversive things but
in a sense the reason they're defined as
attractive or aversive is entirely in
relation to the behaviors they
elicit
yes I I think this also relates to the
first principles partitioning of
pragmatic and epistemic value in active
inference so if we were dealing with a
CO with a purely cost based data
sampling method so something different
than the approach taken this paper then
we might find a way to add in different
epistemic features or her istics and
make a
cost
objective that could
Encompass uh various elements of like
novelty and so on however we would still
only end up with one monolithic
cost-based still
pragmatic objective whereas the approach
taken in this paper was to actually
start with the costree p epistemic
elements of Information Gain and then
from there cost can be brought in but
then it is clearer how the costs
associated with sampling are not of the
kind that the epistemic gain is whereas
if you start with a cost reward
pragmatic utility Etc based model then
the only real method is to bring in the
costs or values of information but then
that ends up all kind of dumping into
the same Silo and it can't be brought
out back
later yes and it's interesting thinking
about those two different strands um
partly just historically
thinking you could regard active
inference and the the the approach that
we sort of outlin in this in this paper
as being a point of convergence between
several different strands of what you've
been going on for many many years before
this
so there's a lots of people would think
of it in terms of how things like
expected utility Theory or reinforcement
learning or those approaches that are
based upon the idea of a cost might have
now have uh Incorporated Information
Gain like terms into those cost
functions um but the other way of
thinking about it is that there's a long
tradition in things like Basin
experimental design and optimal
experimental design so much more from
the the the question of how do we best
design experiments
um or even feature selection um from
particular data sets to try and work out
how best to draw inferences from it um
and you could argue that that those
sorts of entirely reward cost-free
approaches that have then
been u based upon how do I get the most
information out of these things are now
being equipped with a cost
function so you could see it from either
perspective and really this is this is
one way you could go from either way you
could either say am I trying to equip my
cost with Information Gain or am I
trying to equip my information gain with
the cost of
something yes meeting in the
middle but it really does depend where
it starts
from um Chris want to add anything or or
we can continue
I think um I don't know can you guys
hear
me okay um what I really appreciate
about kind of the cost in this uh on
that topic uh in this aspect is that it
is very useful sense of when do we not
care about what we're
gaining um at what point do we say hey
we've made enough it's good enough and I
think
it's it's paralleled to a lot of the
costs that we have in other models but
it's also own unique thing where you're
just saying hey you know we don't need
to sample more we don't need to go with
the full factoral like sort of like
sampling design we've gotten to the
point that we are satisfied with the
information that we have gained here and
we can move on with kind of the next
steps of actually using that data in
some way um what's really nice about it
is that it know if you equip the cost to
your situation appropriately you can
really reduce sort of
the time it takes to sift through large
amounts of data or kind of through the
monetary cost of actually collecting
that data um because
that's we're in a big data world but
still a lot of areas that just don't
have a lot of big data that you can
actually utilize you have to collect it
yourself and so you're actually doing
the concept of cost dat sense to a
literal monetary value I think that
makes it infinitely usable uh in
Industry spaces
so pretty sure Thomas want to add
anything or we or we can move on to some
of the pieces that we didn't get to in
the dot one
I have I have a few questions of my own
but I would very much like to get on to
some of the things we didn't do in the
the dot one just initially okay I think
the main area that we held off for so
maybe we can cover it and then and then
sort of just in the in the openness see
where it goes was section
six um so for review in the one other
than Carl's amazing Exposition in
defense of epistemic value we walk
through a few the fundamental formalisms
and got essentially on up through figure
five with a dynamically changing setting
and spoke a little bit about the uh the
similarities and differences with the
maximum entropy based
sampling then several pieces come into
play in section
six um
they close section five saying we
address next we address active sampling
in a situation where analytical
Solutions are no longer possible so
there's a few things happening first is
that the the loss of the analytic
character where the generative process
and the generative function have the
same form that's what is going to
motivate this kind of variational
proximation and then also there's the
sheer fact of bringing in the cost and
the
relevance of the clinical trial setting
so maybe to kind of set up this example
Thomas you're a
clinician what did you bring in or how
did you bring together this research
section and ground it in what you felt
was going to be helpful and meaningful
for clinical
settings well I think you've you've
highlighted of the key sentences already
and that's the idea that when we're you
know as as a theoretician often the
sorts of simulations that I'll end up
building are those that work relatively
well in an analytic setting or or where
a lot of the problems are relatively
easy to solve uh and and that's
certainly the case for some of the
earlier simulations in April
um however there anything to be
practically useful you often need to go
far beyond those those domains and you
need to work with problems that are
sometimes not linear uh don't have clear
analytic ways of of
solving um but it was also trying to
think so so it was trying to think
what's a good example of something
that's a bit more realistic a bit more
like what people might do in
practice um the other part of it is is
trying to think what's a really good
example of something where there's a
really obvious cost but also it's really
important to gain information about it
um and clinical trials are quite an
obvious example when you start thinking
about it in those terms where there is
some uncertainty about the benefit of a
particular therapeutic intervention
whether that be a new drug or surgical
procedure or whatever else um and if you
knew the answer to this if you knew
whether it was effective or not or or or
even harmful that could um make a big
difference in terms of your cost
function because you can benefit some
people relative um to to if you hadn't
offered them that
intervention um so here here there's
this sort of
interesting um combination of those two
things uh and and you think about how
how a lot of these trials work in
practice and in some cases they end up
stopping early either because they've
just become so convinced of the benefit
of the effect that it seems unethical
now to have a control on where you don't
give people the treatment or if they
started to become convinced that it the
intervention is harmful and therefore
the trial should be stopped so as Not to
cause any more harm um so there's
already implicitly a lot of these
evaluations and these tradeoffs going
into this domain um and so I thought it
would be really interesting to try and
unpack that um explicitly and formally
to see how we might might start to to
deal with this in a simulated context
but in one that could be applied um in
in in quite an important
real world
question
okay so here in
14 we have delightfully stated the whole
joint distribution so maybe could you
summarize equation 14
here yes so um equation 14 was a way of
writing down something very much like um
Klan Meer uh type survival analysis um
function but in in WR WR written down in
terms of a basian generative model and
something that could actually generate
some data um so these sorts of survival
analyses essentially look at the time or
or or look at the probability over time
that someone has experienced an event
and what survival would come if that
event is death that we're looking
effectively how many people have
survived over time and the shape of that
function then you can compare that with
different um different function shapes
uh to see the the ratios between them
which intervention led to Greater
survival
essentially uh it doesn't necessarily
have to be um death it could
be um it could be acquisition of a
particular symptom it might be a
positive thing so you might actually
want to to um to flip it the other way
around you know the time until sudden
recovery threshold has been
um but essentially you've got people
moving from one category into another um
and tradition in a survival analysis
that would be from alive to dead and
you're trying to then M that out but but
again it doesn't necessarily have to be
so mid and can even be a positive
category
move um so the way this is constructed
here um I think our y
variable is uh the the let me try to
remind myself as a while since I've
looked at this uh so the Y variable will
be whether or not or or depending on how
many people you're looking at the
proportion of people who survived to a
particular time
Point um the the high tow variable
that's underlined in blue is going to be
the time we've chosen to sample to check
how many people have survived in this
analysis uh and then we have another
number of other parameters that are
going to be potenti entially relevant in
um in explaining
that um
the Theta variable here uh which is
underlined in purple is going to be the
effect of our intervention or anything
else that that might be relevant and you
can see that's making use of a design
Matrix which is this X on the the lowest
Row The Columns of which are each going
to represent different sorts of
potential explanatory variables
stop me if I'm jumping around too much
as I as I do this um but you can imagine
this X or the multiplication between X
and Theta being very much like a
standard General linear equation of
exactly the kind that you might use in a
regression
analysis um the F variable uh is a set
of temporal basis functions so the point
of this is that we can now start to
estimate a time varying survival
function so something that that is bit
more uh interesting than than just a
simple sort of exponential
decay and the relevance that might be a
time since a particular intervention
might there might actually be variations
in terms
of survive or experience particular
outcome as a consequence of uh the time
since an intervention was put in place
it might might work for a short period
of time and then stop working for
instance um then I think the D andv here
are um additional explanatory variables
okay so V is the randomization ratio we
choose or or sorry which group someone
was randomized to it's a categorical
variable uh and that's chosen by our
variable pi r so pi r is going to be the
um whether we've chosen to randomize uh
in various different proportions so I
think here the options were to randomize
in know a one to two a 1: one or a 2:1
ratio between placebo group and
Interventional
group um so depending upon those will
sample a value for V and that will tell
us which group somebody has ended up in
um and the row variable here is just
giving the um survival function so this
is effectively just a sigmoidal function
at each point in time saying whether
somebody has survived up until that time
point and you can see that that's the
product of that over a series of
discrete time points
um uh and the reason for that is that
we're effectively saying if I have
survived one time point then I'm in F to
may or may not survive to the next time
point and then I'm in the cohort of
people who may to the next time point
which is why it's that product over time
so cumulatively the number of people who
have not experienced the outcome should
drop at each point in
time uh and again the sigmoidal function
at each time point is just to make sure
that that's in between zero and one so
that one would be
everybody avoids the outcome and zero
would be everybody experiences the
outcome from one category to the
next the key thing to bring out of this
is that the two choices I can make
represented by pi as to how I sample my
data are um are when I choose to follow
someone
up um and what randomization ratio I
choose and each of these are going to be
the things that are subject to our
constraints based upon our our pragmatic
value cost which here is going to be the
want for people to
survive or to avoid the the negative
outcome and the randomization ratio will
also affect that same and and and the um
sorry and the Information Gain that I'm
going to achieve by doing
this and so the idea here was that we
will carry on gaining information about
the shape of these survival functions
until the cost of gaining more
information or the benefit of gaining
more information is less than the cost
of randomizing to the R
Group awesome thank you so we see it in
its joint
distributions specification form in
equation 14 and then figure 9 the top
with the graphical
form okay so then let's briefly Walk On
Through To The figure we then have
equation 15 16 17 giving details about
how the variational lause is being
applied to the Joint distribution before
anything to add on
this I don't know how How Deeply you
want to go into it but essentially the
importance of these things is is just
that we're now to deal with
approximations and because the form of
the generative model on the previous
slide was quite nonlinear uh it becomes
much more difficult to solve in an
analytic way uh so what we can do is
make use of various components of a um
of an expansion um around different
gradients and HS so this is looking up
to up to second order um and that's
quite useful in that those same
quantities are the onsters that come up
in um I think the lowest row here is
effectively the penultimate row is a
mutant scheme to optimize variational
for energy uh and a variational for
energy under plus approximation requires
exactly these gradients and heskin so
first and second derivatives in order to
be able to to this sort of problem cool
yeah there's probably a lot to say on
the math but one part that I always find
fascinating is however
these distributions are shaped whether
they're with a central tendency like a
gaussian or whether they have some other
kind of structure the variational lause
is going to fit a parabola basically
facing down over the central tendency
and so there's places where that's
misleading or not but it's just so
interesting to see here how you stepped
through and we can still Trace out what
those variables mean and then by looking
at the the properties
of the distributions as specified it's
like there's this incremental
optimization scheme that will put a
central tendency on the distribution so
it's a it's it's really getting at what
the variational approximation is which
is there's some family of function that
maybe
is completely intractable but then we
can choose to treat the distributions in
a way where it is possible for us to
shift and scale and tune an upside down
Parabola and then that has a well-
behaved
property so it's cool um okay and then
we get can I yeah go ahead can I just
ask sorry on that on those
approximations there um is it the case
that with respect to this approximation
that we assume the distribution is quite
tightly peaked about the mean so we have
quite a precise approximate posterior is
that is that the case no you don't need
to assume that it's tightly um you just
have to assume that there's a reasonable
approximation around
that in fact I'm trying to see whether
it's obvious from these equations
um slightly different form to to what
I'm used to but I just wondered if that
that was the case the answer is no then
so no
so the the reason that that sometimes
comes up is that if you are trying to
derive a variation of a plus procedure
often part of that procedure is is said
saying that at some point you
effectively say that all I need to do is
work directly with the mode rather than
working with both the mode and the
variance and the reason for that is that
the the variance or covariance and the
posterior should just be in an well not
necessar antic but a function of the
mode in relation to the probability
density you have and that's that that's
evident in the in the lower part of um
final equation here so Precision here uh
is dependent directly on the Hessian
evaluated at the mode and that's why why
we're looking the maximum iteration
where we've reached hopefully the mode
of that
distribution um now it it sometimes
seems that to go from a free energy
functional where we're taking an
expectation under the posterior to one
where we can effectively neglect the um
the the variance to um to just deal with
the mode one way you can think about
that is if I were to assume that the
mode is so sharply peaked that there is
no variance to deal with and then the
expectation just becomes a Delta
function you can just evaluate directly
at
mode uh and and that certainly will get
used in very similar equations and
you'll end up sort of arriving at a m
esate the other approach to this is to
say that if I'm assuming that the um
posterior is approximately gausian in
other words that the the log probability
of my data and explan variables are
approximately
quadratic um then it means that
expanding up to a second order term so
making a tailor series approximation up
to the the quadratic element I can
assume that that quadratic element is
effectively constant in the region I'm
I'm dealing with
it um that means that when and that that
quadratic bit is effectively our our
posterior Precision or our negative
exterior precision as you can see in the
sort of final plot
here
um so the point I'm trying to make here
is that that um although it one
intuitive way of of deriving some of
these same quantities is to say well
let's throw away the variance and
imagine we're just doing a map estimate
a maximum apost estimate um then you'll
arrive at very similar modes however the
variance and the posterior Co variance
can actually be recovered
under this assumption that that you're
treating it as being approximately alian
at least close to the mode around which
you're
estim
yeah yeah it's explored in SPM I see the
variational Applause as mode seeking and
then secondarily estimating how spread a
parabola should be which isn't a normal
distribution CU a parabola drops off
whereas if you do the variational
gaussian then you actually are jointly
tuning the mean SL mode and the variance
parameter and then you do have the Tails
going off into the probability
distribution well what what what you
should remember there though and so
you're exactly right to talk about the
mode seeking behavior and and fitting a
parabola um but remember that the
parabola we're talking about so this
quadratic function is actually being
used to fit the log probability not the
probability
itself and if your log probability is of
a quadratic form then you are dealing
with a ging distribution and in fact it
is the coefficient of the quadratic term
that is then your Precision where you're
inverse
covariance thank you great addition okay
we get to figure nine so it's in it's in
the medical journal what does it mean
what is it saying
um so when when you're looking at
probably the easiest thing to look at
here
um would be sorry I'm just
minimizing video so I can see it
clearly uh yeah
so the sort of thing you might see in a
medical journal would often be a
survival curve that looks a bit like the
prediction curve that you see here often
it's more stepwise in terms of how how
it's expressed and that's to do with
form of of KL Meer
estimators um and
the the way in which you'd read that is
that the Y AIS is showing the number of
people the proportion of people who have
yet to experience an event and often
that event is is either a particular
kind of clinical outcome or sometimes
lost to followup which is another thing
that always needs to be incorporated in
then you end up in questions about sort
of censorship of data which essentially
means how do I deal with data I no
longer have access
to um and and the xaxis here is is time
so at each point along the x- axis I'm
asking between these two curves each of
whom represent a population of people
who have or have not been exposed to an
intervention um uh what's the difference
in terms of the proportion of people who
have not yet experienc an
event so that event might be a heart
attack or a stroke or
and you know various other things that
you might pick out as being clinically
relevant and the key thing really is
trying to understand how do these how
how does either different interventions
or even the absence of an intervention
or more commonly a placebo
intervention uh differ and that allows
you to estimate the effect of a
particular um therapy that you might
want to
choose awesome so here we have the
random sampling in figure 9 for the
randomized control trial so in this
situation there was randomization of
50/50 and then the choices as shown here
are are uniformly scattered throughout
the the duration of the study then yeah
you build in the
[Music]
um deliberate choice of follow-up time
and random ization by combining the
general message passing with the
information uh gain imperative here and
we get to figure 10 so what is different
in figure
10 well I mean the other thing I'll just
point out is um so the choices here are
both the choices about follow-up time
and also the choices about randomization
so the size of the dots uh representing
each choice uh represents and I'm afraid
I can't remember which way around this
is but the number of people who are
randomized for each group so three
different size dots one of which
represents uh one3 in the placebo group
one of which represents half in the
placeo group and one of which represents
two3 in the placeo
group so it is actually and you're right
to say it's it's deciding a completely
uniform way in the um first figure just
to illustrate what would happen if we if
we just decided these things at random
say nobody ever decides these things
just at random it's a bit more rational
there
often pre-specified followup
time or even in Bas adaptive type
clinical trials there'll be criteria
that been m in terms of when people have
followed up and how the randomization
works but we're comparing to a slightly
um straw man example of if we were to
completely randomize and just pick
things entirely at random
um so the difference between figures
is it figure nine and 10 is that in
figure 10 we've now um now now put the
information gain as one of the key
things we need to make use of and so
here it's going to adjust the
randomization as it goes to try and and
make sure it learns uh most about what
happens in each of these different
conditions so it's more uncertain about
the trajectory in one condition um it
will it will assign more people to that
condition and vice Versa until it's got
more precise estimates hopefully of each
of these
lines um it's also going to change where
it solves and you can see that there's a
slight um a slight shift I think towards
later in the trial one of the reasons
for that is that the later the follow-up
time the more informative that is about
all the previous follow-up times if I
observe someone early on and see that
they've survived that doesn't
necessarily tell me how much longer
after that they've survived whereas if I
observe someone at the end and and know
that they've survived that tells me they
probably well that tells me they've
definitely survived throughout all of
the preceding D points as well um so
there's a little bit more information to
be gathered towards the end compared to
at the beginning so there's a little bit
of a shift in that direction what's not
done in this particular uh simulation is
uh any cost or any preference for people
surviving which obviously is a very
important thing to include in any
realistic decision
making I think that's going to be the
Fig we look so then you layer in the
cast in 11 so explain this
one yeah uh so F first thing I tried
doing with this one actually was was
just putting a general preference for
observing someone surviving the issue
was it then just selected all of the the
points at the very beginning of the
trial um because everybody survives at
the beginning nobody had time to
experience the AL um which if you prefer
seeing people survive is is actually a
completely reasonable thing to do um but
what we really want is for people to
survive for the duration of the
trial so here here there's a um a sort
of increasing function of prence that
says I I prefer to see people having
survived at the very end which is of
course also weighted with this potential
information gained to and one of the
things you'll see here is that it
relatively rapidly switches it Behavior
to randomize more people to uh the
placebo group which is the group in in
pink and that seems like a very
reasonable thing to do because a as
things progress you can see that the
placebo group even though it's less
confident than on the previous slide it
learns that the placebo group um
actually survive better than the
treatment group so in this particular
case the treatment would not be a good
treatment it's actually
harmful um and this is analogous to the
idea of stopping early in a clinical
trial because you're you're concerned
about the effect that your intervention
is having
um and so I think this is this is sort
of encouraging to see that it's um it's
behaving in the right way it's um it's
saying actually more people survive and
don't experience this delerious outcome
if they have the placeo so as I become
more and more confident of that I'll
randomize more people for Placebo arm uh
and the end conclusion of this is that
everybody would be randomized that are
and in a sense this is this almost blurs
the boundaries
between between the information seeking
which is the primary IM of a clinical
trial and the public health imperative
to try and um make available the the
best treatments that that are going to
be most effective and to not give people
treatments that are going to cause them
harm but by trading off exploration and
exploitation sort of traditional um
sense we can actually blur the
boundaries between those two things and
gather information until we've reached
the point where actually the amount we
could potentially gain from that
information is less than the
cost that that's having on people who
are randomized to the wrong
group thank you it's very interesting in
light of our earlier discussion on the
sort of reward first or epistemic first
when we think about the hypocritic oath
like Do no harm do no evil and then it
immediately comes in well what about a
blood draw and this is going to cause
harm oh well there's a a better benefit
but then that is still all cast and
reduced down to the expected benefits
and
utilities which leaves Information Gain
kind of out in the cold as something
that can't really be compared or brought
in whereas this is in in certain C ways
blurring a line
that gives that there's a lot of
structures around that line between what
is health research and what is public
health and
so helping paint that it is blurred in
practice and that the formalism brings
Clarity to
that Fusion imperative rather than
blurring what was clear is a it's a very
I mean it's a society shifting concept
that would change how studies and
day-to-day Health could be
done and I I think in many ways it is
done already at an implicit level I mean
I think a large a large part a large
number of the decisions that um is
any any doctor is making on a day-to-day
basis um revolves around do I have more
to gain by getting this new piece of
information versus the potential cost of
doing this to the patient the Health
Service to society in general um
and um you know do you do you treat
somebody early before you're completely
sure about what condition they might
have or do you wait until you gather
more information but potentially risk
them deteriorating in that time um so
there's there's always a lot of these
trade-offs happening in clinical
practice I think implicit they are
already happening in at the level of
these sorts of trial dists as well that
people do stop trials early um or or or
do use adaptive trial designs where they
can change the parameters based on
what's happened probably means they AR
implicitly using these same um uh ideas
without necessarily formalizing this
way so in a sense I in a sense I think
it you know is maybe an endorsement of
that approach rather than necessarily
saying people should do differ I think
in many ways people are already
doing yeah um from the help oh yeah
Chris Chris go
ahead I was just wondering because you
you what's I like about this figure that
and you much said it outright is that it
it shows kind of a stopping early sort
of uh modality in the study where you
know you're shifting more people towards
the placebo group you're effectively
more less just saying you know it's not
worth it anymore um what was interesting
to me or I guess what I'm wondering is
there's also the C the counter to that
that you could you know in a different
scenario say hey this is working really
well um we're going to put more people
into the treatment group absolutely fine
but is there a way that you can embed
kind of extending the time into some of
these models or decreasing the time
they're just saying at some point hey
it's no longer worthy of me continuing
to randomize people here it's just let's
stop here this is kind of that cost
function can you optimize the cost
function
to um either decrease or increase the
time so that you can get the most
benefit from The Trial that's kind of my
what I was
wondering yeah um no absolutely and I
think um I think sort of changing the
the time parameter is another one of the
key things that that you I mean in a
sense you could argue that that that
this um choice of when to follow up is
precisely that um that that that
actually it's already to some extent
doing that um and it would be
interesting to trade off the costs uh in
terms of the information lost when
people are lost to followup and those
sorts of things as well in an more
realistic model relative still
relatively simplistic one we forward
here
um but I I think it's to take your point
more generally as well it's it's really
interesting to think about what are the
parameters not just in a clinical trial
but in any any um any sort of
experimental design or policy decision
what are the key parameters that you
have control over and what are the
effects of those parameters on the
information you might gain and on the
preference you might have the different
kinds of outcome and in principle any of
these that you can form at in in a clear
way uh you you can use these sorts of
approaches to start to try and optimize
and choose in a principled
way
and I think that's fantastic I'm kind of
thinking through
now
um you know survival is a pretty binary
like outcome you know it's you're you're
dead or you're alive
um it's a very clean system to try this
out in when do you start getting into
more Nuance health benefits so if you're
looking for possibility of um you're if
you're tweeting somebody with a
myocardial infraction or faction however
you want to say that um and you're
trying to treat them with a drug that is
supposed to change an arisia in their
heart or something of that nature
um you'll see smaller Gaines instead of
just like alive or dead you hoping the
patient lives regardless in both cases
but you're not really measuring death
you know how does this sort of model
change when you start to look at
more distributed
data I think I of that sorry that the
sound is still a little bit quiet but I
I if I could summarize I think the
question is it effect ly one of yes is
obvious that that if if your outcomes
are life or death that there there's a
clear distinction in terms of
preferences I might want to have for
those things um but there are a number
of things that are much more nuanced and
may have trade-offs in themselves um
that that um it becomes a little bit
harder and less obvious as to how to
assign preferences degrees of preference
um and so you always get back to the
what is often quite a generic issue as
to how do I choose my priors how do I
choose my degree and in this case it's
the prior preference that I'm choosing
how how do I select that um and there
are a couple of a couple of interesting
approaches that people take so one would
be to say well let's actually look at
what people already do settings when do
people set these criteria early stopping
the trial or or whatever
else um can you then invert that process
and then infer what the implicit cost
function they were using was or what the
implicit prior preferences were uh and
then that might be a way of of then just
formalizing that and saying Okay so this
clearly is the the relative preference I
have for these different outcomes
relative to The Information Gain that
might be one way of approaching it um
the other the other approach I mentioned
at the beginning of of the session last
week that a lot of this had sort of come
out of um initially attending a a
workshop in Australia um in Sydney where
a lot of the discussion was around
basing networks and how you select PRI
and a lot of people there um work on
work on the problem of um elicitation
and how you how you take uh focus groups
or samples of the population or key uh
key groups who are invested in a
particular problem stakeholders uh and
how you extract from their views and how
you how you ask questions in the right
way to be able to get out prior that
matter to them or that that they see
they take to be
relevant and that's obviously
particularly used in contexts where the
PRI are uncertain and you want some
expert views or there's limited
information you want some way of
constraining um uh a particular prior
for a particular setting but I think
it's also potentially very useful in
terms of writing down the right kind of
preferences here so you could imagine if
you asked enough people who might be
relevant stakeholders in in a particular
outcome how much do you value this over
that and and and do a number of
comparisons there you could con start
you could start to construct the
relevant cost function because the
relevant cost function here is often
going to be for the people who For Whom
the intervention is offered and so um
those of us who are not necessarily the
beneficiaries of it or or people who
might be harmed by it are probably not
the right people be setting
preferences finding out a way of
engaging the relevant people and taking
account of their views on it and how
those might be incorporated into private
preferences I think is a a really
interesting and not entirely solved
question could I could I jump in with a
quick question as well please so if I
may be so bold uh the sh shall we say
The Guiding normativity of the let's you
know the various uh simulations that
were offered in the p
was something like at least initially uh
the degree of expected Information Gain
that one is is able to Asain at a
certain point in time as a consequence
of a certain intervention or not and now
we're running into the issue of uh this
let's call that the cost function
perhaps this is this is what we're going
to perhaps use as our proxy for the
relevant thing to do at the relevant
time for the relevant population and so
on but we're coming up against issues
now of uh yes but there are the question
as to the relevant uh you know action is
not merely reducible to expected
Information Gain at you know as a
consequence of a certain action there
are meta considerations like ah we would
like to observe people living throughout
the trial basically so we don't want to
just have you know people be observed to
be living at the beginning of the trial
uh you can do expected information G
perfectly fine with all of that but
there is this matter consideration um of
the way in which we're going to you know
solicit uh preferred observations that
doesn't seem to be just reducible to
expected Information Gain so a lot of my
particular you know interest are in well
how do we how do we map out that sort of
space it perhaps expected information
game could could be you know exacted
into this larger space of considerations
um one might think but but that's that's
a very interesting problem that I think
you said as well was it's an incredibly
difficult problem um and it wasn't it
certainly wasn't the focus of this paper
um so it's a bit unfair to to to lay
upon you um you know questions as to
okay well what what might guide those
those higher order considerations but
that that is something that I thought
was would be very interesting to discuss
maybe later or or
now as you as you've raised it now
should we discuss it now yeah unless it
was I mean I think you're exactly right
that expected Information Gain on itself
is not enough um in in at least in some
settings I think in some settings it
probably is an
ins um and and that almost begs the
question in how do you know whether to
put more emphasis on expected
Information Gain on other forms of
cost and I should say that the the sort
of addition of cost into this is partly
relevant in the sense that as in
relevant to the expected Information
Gain in that it's only when you have a
good quantification of the cost of or or
or the benefit of of gaining information
cost of not gaining that information
that you can actually start to do that
tradeoff um so although it it can
sometimes feel a little bit arbitrary
that you're just sort of adding another
term to the the objective function but
actually the only reason you could do
that is because by expressing them in
exactly the same units and the same
Notions different kinds of probability
distribution uh or or log probabilities
or potentials it's only by by being able
to put them in that same space you can
even start to do this tradeoff um which
is the reason it was relevant to ruce
the cost
function in addition to that in this
setting obviously the other approach
that we might take in active inference
is actually to go from first principles
try and derive something that looks like
um expected free energy that is already
a combination of these things and then
can be pulled apart to see how it
contributes to both these sorts of costs
and Information
Gain um and I
think clearly putting the right sort of
costs so that you will only seek out
information if it doesn't lead to
something that is very very aversive and
um and vice versa you'll only seek out
things you prefer if there's also some
scope to gain information at least
relative to other actions you might take
I think is useful in allowing these
things to contextualize
one and that's something call but very
well last session we
did what what were your thoughts about
it how would you approach that
question I mean I I can't think of any
other way than to sit you've kind of
already said it then to situate the
whole task where uh considering you know
in this case it's it's maybe clinical
design trial design and so on for for
survivability the only way I can really
see to do it is to relate it to the kind
of autopoetic goals of the agents
involved so we maybe we have a met
assumption that all of these agents wish
to continue across time or a certain
subset of them we wish a certain subset
of them to continue across time given
certain
considerations um that I'm I'm just
spitballing here but I don't really see
how to situate The Guiding normativity
in anything other than the continuation
of of the the the you know sensor motor
Loop of a particular subset of the the
the uh you know agents under
consideration of course then that raises
the question well which subset do we
want
so we sort of have a recapitulation of
the same issue so to sum up I have no
idea but um that's that's the only
really thing that comes to mind if we
can somehow tie this to
the the you know the ways in which
autopoetic beings are able to maintain
their AIS across time
um if anyone else has a better of
suggestion um that's that's as far as
I've been able to get so
far okay what what that makes me think
about is something like a um semantic
supply chain for this for the clinical
study so it's like we didn't assess in
this
paper should we do a clinical study but
there's another room where that's a
question it's like well what could we
stand to learn what would the cost be
and then some and then someone so
somebody says should we do this clinical
study and then someone's like should you
have taken the policy to ask if we
should have done the clinical study and
someone's like yeah I didn't know so I
asked to find out
and then that's where the buck stops
because right there you can say here's
where there was a
definable
uncertainty that was actionably
addressed and that's how it propagated
on through to the clinical
study and then and then um all along the
way counterfactuals could be
analyzed like if it were 10 times more
costly to sequence The genome
then we would have had done this study
but then that also opens the door to
when the cost of something is lower that
another study could be done
um there's this element of the
participatory stakeholder involvement
and asking people questions that that
keeps it grounded
but uh and it's it's obviously such a
generic situation that there aren't
strong answers but just the idea of
Tracing Our un uncertainties and
preferences and Norms back on through to
the cognition of the study
design seems to take it into a place
that's going far beyond just trying to
sample optimally from a
population because it calls into
question like what does optimal sampling
if the people so strongly don't want to
be sampled then what is this kind of
optimal sampling protocol actually
sampling it's all it's all maybe
somewhat moot obviously because in this
example we are doing you know beijan
optimal trial design a lot of those
questions are going to be you know sort
of posed and answered for us so trying
to trying to make it more General is is
maybe maybe just a false errand maybe
there isn't uh a way to generalize that
other than to swim in the waters of the
particular situation we're
considering and of course it's a very
Noble and worthwhile thing to consider
Vision optimal tra trial design so
perhaps not much of a
problem well I mean I think you're right
to think about how to try and generalize
the problem and arguably
the the answer is exactly the same way
exactly as Daniels described you could
could say the question of actually
designing this child that's Bas thinking
of doing it is itself something that
comes with potential Information Gain
potential cost
benefits um and that actually a lot of
behavior is based well almost all
Behavior where I select between
alternative things I could do is going
to be based upon similar desires to both
explore to find out and uh to explore
which once I know that I can satisfy
certain
preferences um arguably it's only by
doing those things that that you can
maintain your persistence over time in
exactly the way you
describing that possibly is one of the
key imperatives for any sort of creature
that can um envisage alternative paths
forwards and select
between to the public playing the game
oh go fure sorry go oh sorry I was just
gonna say to to keep playing the game
basically is is the uh yeah the
answer I think there's
another uh way that this comes into play
with the health study versus is just
Public Health in a health study often
times just like laboratory studies in
general there is you want to make a a
control group that's actually like a
valid comparison like if you're studying
the effect of food X versus not you
really want to make sure that people who
ate it ate it and who didn't eat it
didn't eat it because you're trying to
to make maximally separable whereas if a
given Health intervention or or program
were driven to to a large extent by
pragmatic consideration like we want to
reduce the prevalence of this in this
population then that would plug into
many other policies that could come into
play so instead of like we're going to
study whether a daily email can help
with this health condition and then you
want to then the whole imperative of the
researcher okay we want to make sure
those emails were delivered or not
versus if we pull back and say okay they
want these people to have less of this
disease and here's how that is being
balanced with reducing uncertainty about
the effects of
email then somebody else maybe that
group or another group could pick up on
the pragmatic
consideration and then plug in with a
different policy so from that pure
epistemic standpoint it's like oh but
now this is like less of a controlled
experiment and it's like well yes that
is the tradeoff that is
being
finessed is the frontier with who does
what when there are both things that are
uncertain but there are things that we
could be uncertain and simply be unsent
to us and then we don't need to take the
policies to reduce uncertainty because
the Information Gain even if it was a
lot could be just like well you could
look at a a block of random text and you
could reduce your uncertainty a lot but
then that is not usually selected
because it's not aligned with other
preferences and that but that also I
think the example of looking at a block
of text is an interesting one as to why
why you might not do that even though it
might resolve your uncertainties to
what's on the page because you also need
to think about what else it might
resolve your uncertainty about um so if
you are curious about something or do
not know something and that block text
will tell you it then it may be quite a
useful thing to read that block of text
whereas looking just to see the
particular wording about something you
already know about about some sorry
terrible English isn't it the the the
wording of something about which you you
already know then there's not much um
there's not much Point looking at it is
though it's sort of a waste of of time
and energy because it's already um some
some uncertainty that you you don't even
have to resolve you don't have that
uncertainty in the first place uh
similarly you might not know something
and the text may still not arguing about
it in other words it's quite ambiguous
text because it doesn't help resolve
between the alternative
hypotheses um and I guess this comes
down to an interpretation of expected
Information Gain or the mutual
information between your hypotheses and
the data that you could measure um and a
mutual information can always be
separated into two entropies so one of
them is an entropy that is um how
uncertain am I about what these data
would look like under this under this
plan and the other one the other entropy
is which is subtracted from that is the
conditional entropy so how
ambiguous is this measurement and the
way I would often like to think about
that is there's no point doing an
experiment we already know what the data
would look like um if if I could picture
exactly what I would measure before I
even did the experiment there'd be no
point doing that experiment um because
what am I going to look for and that's
our our predictive entropy that's the
first one which is how uncertain am I
about what I see um but then you have to
account for the amount of information
that you're actually going to be able to
resolve and so subtracting this
ambiguity making sure that that actually
this experiment is going to resolve that
uncertainty it's not just going to be
uncertain noisy data that yes I can't
predict but that's just because I've
used an extremely noisy measuring
instrument that would also be a
pointless experiment to do the right
experiments to do are the ones where I
couldn't predict the
data uh based upon what I know already
but that the conditioned upon a
particular hypothesis the data would
actually be very
predictable and so by seeing those data
I can start to really disambiguate
between things that I didn't
already okay in this kind of spirit of
the the block of text there's a lens or
or a frame in which it's just uniform
but then there's another way in which it
might resolve or not okay so there's no
point to do the experiment if you
already know what the outcome would be
but then maybe in that case it would be
something more like a habit or
ritual or even if you have an experiment
that you don't know what the outcome is
going to be there's still procedural
elements of the experiment that you do
want to know the outcome on like the
Intermediate calibrations or
assays so I think this kind of points to
the very rich and and
woven nature of epistemic and pragmatic
value and why it's so important to have
an accounting system
that
can hold them up side by side because
even on one
action there might be many ways or
different scales of a nested model which
that action or the
consequences are are being chosen for a
variety of of competing factors and then
sample probabilistically and then the
then the impact on a hierarchy arcal
predictive processing system Also may
not simply fall into an epistemic or a
pragmatic bucket because it could be
epistemically novel at this layer but
then that was exactly what was expected
at another layer but then the fact that
it was expected at that layer was
learning at another layer
um so it's very
interesting yes we spoke last week about
the idea that you can actually use a
form of message passing in spas
generative models to to pick out the
uner or the expected Information Gain
about a particular
State and I think that's an another way
of looking at exactly what you've just
outlined that it may be that there is a
great that one action gives you a lot of
potential Information Gain about a
particular State um but you have to then
encounter The Information Gain that
other states um or about other states in
your model about other things and so
that's a situation where maybe it would
be the wrong thing to do to focus in on
a particular margin and actually what
you want to know is the the um
Information Gain about all of the things
you don't know
about awesome um so so here you might
say do I want to know about the effects
of all the confounding variables or do I
just want to know or do I just want to
estimate the effect of the intervention
so is it relevant for me to characterize
the precise shape of the um of the
function temporal trajectory with those
basis sets or is it sufficient for me to
to just focus on resolving Myer about
the size of the effect of treatment how
different these two plots
are and that that problem you know we we
were speculating
before the issue that I I have in my
mind is well how you decide between
those two uh levels let's say of
information expected information gain
resolvable do you have another meta
expected Information Gain between the
two say the lower level you know which
basis functions should I have versus the
you know which approach should I even
take at
all that's that's a question that I I
find particularly interesting scaling
all the way up to the previous example
that that Daniel mentioned you know well
should I should I even do the
intervention at all um I know that does
that that that comes quite a far field
from the subject of the paper but um
that's very much gets into the question
of of well exactly what level is
relevant what what Information Gain is
relevant and how do we score which one
is
relevant when when we're doing a
clinical trial it's quite obvious
relatively obvious let's say for
sure and perhaps part of that comes back
to the original discussion we were
having about the relevance of different
sorts
of um States and distributions and
obviously this is a very subjective
thing exactly as you were talking about
Rel realization the idea that it's not
it's it's both about myself and my model
and the environment that I'm dealing
can't take one away from the other um
and probably a large part of that does
come down to the Precision ascribed to
different sorts of of mappings where
those mappings are going to be
conditional probability
distributions um and the perhaps
voluntary attentional
waiting um deployment of different
Precision values to different parts of
of your
model and you could argue that that if
you were to do this at a higher level
you might be able to use it from
empirical prior over what might happen
at a lower level of model as well or
even to contextualize the preferences so
there's no reason why your preferences
or cost function can't be um context
sensitive and in fact the the the really
interesting question comes when you
invert that and you say well locate if
I'm predicting my cost function based
upon the higher La then what I'm doing
at the lower La should be able to tell
me something about the context at the
higher
level so if I believe that in this
circumstance I like doing this whereas
in this circumstance I like doing that
then seeing what I do might then give me
evidence for being in one of those two
different
contexts so it's a really interesting
question is how you might hierarchically
decompose these things and
allow layers and layers of context
sensitivity that then allow me to select
my preferences and also potentially
conditioning my precisions in such a way
that that the balance between um these
exploitive and explorative drives will
vary yes there's there's a um there's a
relatively canonical example that John B
gives on on precisely this issue um you
know imagine you're in an election and
you need to take good not your initial
state is well I don't have good notes
you know what are the possible actions
uh well I could write stuff down I could
type things I could use finger paint the
the affordances and the prediction
errors the Precision of the prediction
errors and the you know the expected
Information Gain at afforded as a
consequence of any particular action is
is very uh undefined it's unspe not
unspecified but it's underspecified and
so the the exact you know low level
routines that you should engage
in the the expected Information Gain is
a consequence of you know any particular
um lowlevel action uh is is relatively
similar to any other one so again that
there is that question of well of
presumably there's going to be something
from a higher order um you know
preference whereby I have in the past
let's say I have built up a model that
ah my laptop is an excellent thing for
me to use to to write down things and
and so forth so that's going to kind of
solve the problem in that case case so
yeah there does appear to be some model
of uh you know hierarchical nesting of
these things in some fashion I know
that's delightfully um nebulous but uh
that's the only that's the only really
thing that that came to mind I was just
wondering if in the inversion of that
particular example if you found yourself
having not taken very good notes you
might then say well if it were a good
lecture I would have wanted to take good
notes so the fact that I haven't wasn't
a very good
lecture that has uh crossed my mind from
time to time
something in there about like if I had
more time I would have written a shorter
letter but I didn't so I must have had
more
time um or the other thing it made me
think of was the back to the streetlight
example so we talked about how the
street light is is
both
Justified but it's also this kind of
like
limitation on one hand that's where we
can resolve our uncertainty but also
that's not the whole story but now we
zoom out a layer and there's a policy on
the electrical grid deciding which
street lights to turn on or how to dim
different street lights and then you
pull back even another layer there's a
construction policy on the street lights
over the decades and then and then at
the nightly scale it's the energy grid
policy so then that agents looking
around information
foraging is happening within slower
scales such that they're not in a
stationary single street light
World they might be looking around and
then spiraling out just like you
described and then that moves them into
a new attractor a new regime of
attention where they're they're sampling
differently from there um so it's kind
of when we read a paper like this and we
see a
motif get built up so methodically
and then always there's this point in
the dot two where even that
Motif is just one puzzle piece swirling
around with the broader question of of
how we make these generative
models when even the motif which looks
awesome and sounds very cool it's very
educational to learn about but then it
is also
just
another element in these broader models
yes and I I think clearly it's a it's a
very I me there are two two big issues
when you're or three big issues when
you're trying to trying to design um
creatures that behave in an active
inference way so one one of those issues
is is um obviously drawing inferences
about the world another one is changing
the world to comply with your
predictions and then the third is um
given the type of evalua first two in
relation to the fit between my model and
the data I currently have the third
question is always how do I deal with
data that I don't yet have and that's
where that's where this sort of generic
issue of
selecting um things so that or selecting
courses of action that lead to
informative um but also preferred data
becomes so
important but you're absolutely right
all of these things are then conditional
upon the model that I that I have in the
first place and that model um will
condition these various other things
that model may say I have very very
precise preferences or very precise
prior beliefs of the sort of outcomes
I'm going to seek out or it might not
and that may be conditionally dependent
upon other things at other levels for
mod which may be subject to exactly the
same generic um objective
functions but because the form of the
model at that level may lead to
different sorts of behavior than you
might anticipate other ones
and so I think you're absolutely right
to to highlight that although there are
these generic motifs the the
optimization of my model fits both by
action and perception and the
optimization of future
data by choosing informative preferred
data points
um are all relevant only in the context
of the models under which they they
act they are of course also ways of
building which is another interesting
point but some of that will be dependent
upon the data that's presented back by
the world and um and and we sort of get
back to some of the discussion we were
having last week about things like
natural selection and the selection
between alternative models alternative
individuals being Alternative forms of
models that that that are selected um
with each
generation so there's a history
dependent El which is dependent upon the
data I've had before for which just
comes down to that question of if I'm
comparing to the data that I've observed
previously and and back to just the
problem of comparing
models finding the most evidence or
finding the models that have
the in the in the conclusion you pointed
towards uh using
sophisticated
inference to approach some of of these
uh situations where you might want to
plan over future observations so where
are you hoping to
develop what is presented in this
paper well I think so the point about
the sophisticated inference scheme and
for those
who haven't come across this the idea is
that um that although I have my
separable objectives to seek out things
I like and things that will inform me
about my my model and my
world um each of those things may also
be dependent upon what I've observed at
earlier points in time so it might be
that having performed a particular
action made an observation and updated
my
beliefs um in relation to the
observation I've got that that will then
change what what might be most
informative at the next step in time or
what might be most rewarding at The Next
Step in Time
so by rolling out my beliefs about uh
what I might do next and conditioning
those upon what I might do after that
and conditioning those upon what I might
do after and more than that conditioning
those on the beliefs I might have at
each of those points um you you can you
can really start to develop much deeper
policies have that recursive aspect that
that um is probably quite familiar to a
lot of people who worked with things
like B and optimality
problems um and one of the things I find
quite interesting about that is that in
in principle you might now do things
that will help me seek out more um
information in the future um as well as
doing things that will gain the
information might help me um achieve
more rewarding observations in the
future um so again they are still
separable but actually it will look like
I'm what what what a lot of people in um
in probably reinforcement learning typ
Fields would be more familiar with the
idea that I might seek out information
to gain reward um if I have a recursive
scheme then it will look like I'm doing
that even if I additionally see
information is having its own unique
value um in and of itself regardless of
whether or not it leads to reward so I
think that's what that's one of the key
reasons for bringing that in here that
that um that I might want to find out
how far someone survived up until this
point so that I can then contextualize
the shape of the function when I know
when they've survived later on or I
might have the option to now put in
multiple follow-up points and actually
if I would to do that independently of
one another um I might put them both in
the same place because that's where I'm
going to getting the most information
however if I would to use a recursive
sophisticated scheme I might say if I
put in this follow-up point then I'll
have resolved all the uncertain need to
about that point so i' better put this
at the other point and so you can now
start to think about multiple followup
points multiple
interventions taking account of of how
one of those might influence the
information you might gain from another
one um so that that was probably the key
point of of putting in that
idea anything you wants to sort of raise
or discuss in in depth on
that yes I think that's where some of
these
computational costs start to expand
however if it can be if if a if a given
situation can even be brought to the
table of sophisticated inference
then it's well set up to do a lot of
interesting analyses and then the other
directions that you
specified empirical evaluation of active
versus alternative sampling methods and
identifying appropriate cost functions
so what about
these yeah uh so I think the empirical
evaluation I think if you were
to if you were to convince probably a
broader Community this is a useful thing
to do then one of the things you'd have
to do would be to show that it
outperforms in a in a very clear way
other schemes that you might want to use
I think there are good principal
theoretical reasons to see how this um
offers some
benefits um however it may be that if
you're dealing with a very nonlinear uh
problem that the cost of even doing all
the computations is to work out what I
should do next might exceed the um
process of actually just doing it or
sing it random one of the things I found
quite interesting is that that actually
when for the for the first couple of
simulations in the paper the random
sampling is actually not much worse than
uh choosing the data very carefully and
one of the reasons for that is that
random sampling will tend to give you a
fairly uniform distribution over over
the points you sampled and assuming that
says uniform uncertainty initially
that's actually a perfectly sensible
thing to do so part of this is not just
about evaluating it for the sake of it
or to to um prove that the theoretical
results translate into something
empirical it's not just about
benchmarking but it's also about finding
where are the places where it can be
most useful clearly we have to have some
sort of addressable way of generating
the data we have to be able to say I'm
going to sample over here or over here
with a set of uniform unlabeled data
points that that that I there's no way
of selecting between that have no
spatial or other
metric in involved um that's going to be
a much harder thing to do in fact it's
going to be impossible thing to do if
there's no sensible way of defining your
policy so I suppose the key thing here
is thinking about when is this approach
useful when will it actually help to
resolve
uncertainty um and in many cases it it
it might not if there is no
um if there is no difference in the
Information Gain between different
options I might take or if that
difference is more or less the same as
what I might get using another strategy
it may be more computationally efficient
to use another sort of
strategy that's that's very um
interesting and the paper set up
accordingly to
this development from the random uniform
to the max ENT
to the full epistemic gain and so each
of those are actually sampling
policies that can be compared and I
guess to um but they're not just samping
policies they're also sampling
situations that I might be in so if I'm
in the sort of situation where ambiguity
varies then it's no longer sensible to
use a maxim mentary type approach so
ultimately You could argue that this
formulation automatically accounts for
these different situations that if I'm
if my model is good enough as an
explanation for the world and how do I
make sure it's good enough I make sure
it's good enough by sing appropriately
drawing those inferences uh but if it's
good enough that I I now have a sense of
how the variance changes as a function
of where I might sample uh if I know
where I'm uncertain where I'm not then
each of these things automatically
becomes a contributory Factor whereas if
I don't know these things or I think the
situation is one in which Things Are
completely uniform then this will now
reduce back to one of the earlier
approaches we were talking about and if
there's no benefit anywhere in terms of
cost no benefit in terms of of the
entropy I might be able to resolve in
terms of objective entropy and if the
ambiguity is the same everywhere then
ultimately this is a random sampling
approach and we'll reduce back to that
so in a sense all of these things are
versions of the same general
problem but the situations in which I
might benefit um from employing
different parts of this are those that
that in which there is difference in
ambiguity in which there is difference
in predictive entropy in which there is
difference in in
cost and so it all comes back to the
model and whether I've got a good model
in my world and my world complies with
these different sorts of
features yes it shifts the focus
from summary performance on a previously
acquired
batch
to more
granular outcomes in a sampling
driven
regime like out of sample prediction
versus looking at in
Sample just how well can you do on what
you already have
versus how surprised are you going to be
about your prediction about what you
haven't seen yet and then this even goes
a little bit further which is how would
you
decide which things that you haven't
seen to get data on and then how would
you assess the cost benefits preferences
and the epistemic value associated with
that so that moves it from not just out
of sample sense making
[Music]
however if I take a sophisticated
inference approach then I would say okay
if I put the first follow-up time here
that would resolve my uncertainty my
beliefs would be much more precise about
that time point so the second one I
should put somewhere else and and and
that means you can start to think about
this and plan this before you even start
doing the
experiment um it also I mean you can see
them serially like that but also it
matters in terms of way youve relative
to one another so you might not need to
put first follow-up point right in the
middle if it's better to have it
slightly earlier to characterize that
bit of the function so that you can put
the other one slightly
later so it is just having a sense of
how each of these things would change my
beliefs in such a way that I can then
take account of that when when dealing
with the other choice and you could roll
that out for a whole series of potential
future follow-up points and sampling
decisions right right so that I mean
that clearly does give us a sense of
maybe higher
considerations than excellent stuff yeah
my my only other question was with
respect to the issue of uh you know
affording computational tractability and
and and affordability and so on has had
you seen any uh you know potential ins
or Avenues to uh maybe instead of things
like sophisticated inference to use
Federated inference and sort of belief
sharing approaches where perhaps we have
you know several
agents communicating amongst themselves
in a joint sort of free energy Minima
minimization scheme with respect to this
um approach I'm very interested on you
know in in whether that would be
applicable here to what extent perhaps
it would be um yeah just very interested
on that that issue no that's a very
interesting point and I you know at a
very simplistic level I I suppose being
able to share beliefs when different
agents have different Advantage points
is is one of the most obvious examples
of that so if I'm if I know what over
here and you know what's over there then
there's no point both of us looking in
both locations if we're able to share
our beliefs directly about what's
happening in each of those locations um
so you can sample with much fewer data
points many fewer data points if someone
else is sampling some of the other ones
um and by optimizing a shared generative
model or passing messages that allow you
to
communicate uh then then that can be
massively beneficial
then if you were to put a a clinical
trial analogy on that you might imagine
that being equivalent to Multi Center
trial something where different groups
across different centers or
countries are jointly contributing to
different parts of that sample space um
so they can jointly optimize a model of
how effective a treatment
is yes as well I I had the thought as
well that you could and we touched on
this the issue of you know well how to
sample or you know where my where my
prize should be for where I sample and
so on um we could see how people have
done it before and do that you could
have some sort of you know imitation
scheme where you say okay well I'm GNA
have certain number of Agents yeah
exactly so yeah that that's just an
interesting Avenue that I thought was
worthwhile to to think about yeah and
and that idea is having um habits passed
down from others um May feed into that
as well because you know as we were
saying it may be that that sometimes the
more computationally efficient thing to
do is to adopt a policy that will always
lead to the same sort of samping rather
than have to compute that policy in you
each time so form sort of armatized um
policy selection which is effectively
prior habits or biases or empirical
prior over what I should do um that
potentially resolve these problems
without me having to to even start to
think about what I might see
yeah that really cuts down on doesn't
doesn't eliminate it but very much
delimits the problem of you know where
your prize come from for these certain
things so very good
stuff well Thomas do you have any last
comments or thoughts or or how do you
see the active data sampling going from
here
um that's a it's a good question isn't
it um where's it going to go from here I
mean I I suppose in a way this is the
same sort of themes that have come up in
a lot of active influence research um it
I think it's going to be interesting
over the next few years seeing how
clinical trial methodology develops I
think there's been a lot more focus in
recent years on things like Bas adaptive
clinical trials possibly some of these
relatively old ideas about how to
optimize experimental design might be
coming back in those sorts of settings
you know particularly in settings where
where the there's quite a rapid change
in evidence and understanding of of
evolving situations pandemics and or
epidemics and the like uh these things
become very very relevant so it'll be
interesting to see how things develop
along those lines and whether they end
up adopting approaches like that we sort
of outl here um but I think it's also as
a lot of what we've discussed has been
the sort of generic issues around
we sample data as well um one of the
difficult issues I think in a lot of
machine learning um approaches is the
the approach of of dealing with very
very large data sets um which are
computationally costly to analyze costly
to
collect
and and not necessarily the there may be
in some circumstances but but in general
may not be the most efficient way of
dealing with the under lying inference
problem um certainly not the most
energetically efficient um so I think
there'll be some
interesting approaches thinking about
how best to optimize that process and
whether part of the process is not just
optimizing the algorithms that do the um
inference based upon those data but
actually optimizing the way in which
those data are selected in the first
place clearly that's a lot of what we as
as living organms do we behave
awesome
Fraser I I only want to say thank you
very very much um Thomas my uh this this
carefully crafted you know um facade of
my relative um you
know I'm extremely grateful to be here
and it's been just amazing so um
although it is early for me but thank
you very much it's been most of like and
hope to do it again well thank you I I
enjoyed learning about um relevance
realization
I may so B to to link
something awesome thank you again Thomas
thank you faser and Chris and see you
all next
time
bye for